Library of Social and Economic Aspects of Medicine of Michael M. Davis,
Library of Social and Economic Aspects of Medicine of Michael M. Davis
- Organizations, Series 4
  Not less interesting are the files on the A.M.A.'s public relations programs, with confidential internal documents of policy and procedures (some conducted by outside surveyors), and documentation of the high-gear efforts of the association to publicize its views about publicly supported health programs. The file contains fascinating documentation on the crisis in the mid-1940s when a noted public relations counseling firm withdrew from its association with the A.M.A. in a dispute over purpose and intention. The bitter battles of the A.M.A. against the programs of the Committee on the Costs of Medical Care, the Committee on the Nation's Health, and findings or recommendations of these and similar bodies are all exposed in Dr. Davis' collection -- a picture of social turmoil in professional-societal relations in flux over many, many years.
  One drawer contains "The A.M.A.-Record," with extensive coverage--in confidential correspondence, secret reports, brochures, clippings, and other published or unpublished formats--of documentation that is beyond value for historical consideration of the battle of the A.M.A. Campaigns and samples of advertising literature are described (with numerous actual examples), the 1948 assessment of $25 and reactions to it, attitudes toward health insurance, folders on medical ethics and economics, tax exemption, etc. Position papers and studies on various legislation such as compulsory health insurance, disability insurance, family doctors, federal aid, health care for the aged, public school systems, Social Security, and veterans care are only part of this exciting story of social change.
  This "record" is further extended by files describing the "A.M.A. in Politics," the National Professional Committee for Eisenhower (1952), action in political campaigns, "Doctors for Nixon-Lodge," and similar efforts that were made over the years to bring the proper forces into line for political action. It is all rather a desperate story, and Dr. Davis' files enhance a view of political battles that is not otherwise available in such completely documented form. Take, for example, the folders on the famous Whitaker and Baxter activities of 1952 to 1954 and the campaign to fight for voluntary medicine described as "one of the choicest plums and hottest potatoes in U.S. public relations," or the file on the National Physicians Committee, and the lobbying activities of the various medical organizations other than the A.M.A.
  - Professional Organizations
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 49)
    - American Association of Medical Social Workers (Box 49)
    - American College of Hospital Administrators (Box 49)
    - American Public Health Association (Box 49)
    - American Sociological Association (Box 49)
    - Association of Labor Health Administrators (Box 49)
    - Hospital Administrators' Correspondence Club (Box 49)
    - National Association of Colored Graduate Nurses, Inc. (Box 49)
    - National Association of Social Workers (Box 49)
    - National Lawyers Guild (Box 49)
    - National League of Nursing Education (Box 49)
    - National Organization for Public Health Nursing, Inc. (Box 49)
    - NY Institute for Hospital Administrators (Box 49)
    - NY State Conference of Social Work (Box 49)
    - NY Academy of Medicine (Box 49)
    - Association of American Dentists (Box 49)
  - General Organizations
    - American Association for Labor Legislation (Box 49)
    - American Association for Social Security (Box 49)
    - American Association of University Women (Box 49)
    - American Farm Bureau Federation (Box 49)
    - American Legion (Box 49)
    - American Social Hygiene Association (Box 49)
    - American Sociological Association (Box 49)
    - American Veteran's Committee (Box 49)
    - America's Town Meeting of the Air (Box 49)
    - Association of American Medical Colleges (Box 49)
    - Boston Dispensary (Box 49)
    - Commission on Financing of Hospital Care (Box 49)
    - Committee for Constitutional Government (Box 49)
    - Commonwealth Fund (Box 49)
    - Cooperative Health Federation of America (Box 49)
    - Disabled American Veterans (Box 49)
    - Farm Foundation (Box 49)
    - Farmers Union (Box 49)
    - Ford Foundation Reports (Box 50)
    - Foundation on Employee Health, Medical Care and Welfare, Inc. (Box 50)
    - Fund for the Republic (Reports) (Box 50)
    - General Federation of Women's Clubs (Box 50)
    - Health Information Foundation (Box 50)
    - Health Insurance Council (Box 50)
    - Independent Citizens' Committee of the Arts, Sciences and Professions (Box 50)
    - Kellogg Foundation (Box 50)
    - Macy Foundation (Research in Social Medicine) (Box 50)
    - Medical Administration Service (Box 50)
    - Medical Economics, Inc. (Box 50)
    - Millbank Memorial Fund (Box 50)
    - Montgomery County Health Fund (Box 50)
    - National Advisory Health Council (Box 50)
    - National Advisory Committee on Local Health Units (Box 50)
    - National Committee for Mental Hygiene (Box 50)
    - National Committee to Uphold Constitutional Government (Box 50)
    - National Conference on Planning for War and Postwar Medical Services (Box 50)
    - National Consumers' League (Cleveland, OH) (Box 50)
    - National Council of Jewish Women (Box 50)
    - National Council of Negro Women (Box 50)
    - National Foundation of Health, Welfare and Pension Plans, Inc. (Box 50)
    - National Fund for Medical Education, Inc. (Box 50)
    - National Grange (Box 50)
    - National Health Assembly (Box 50)
    - National Health Council (Box 50)
    - National Health Federation (Box 50)
    - National Issues Committee (Box 50)
    - National Planning Association (Box 50)
    - National Social Welfare Assembly (Box 50)
    - New York State Commission on Medical Care (Box 50)
    - New York State Department of Labor (Box 50)
    - New York State Insurance Company (Box 50)
    - Planned Parenthood Federation of America (Box 51)
    - Pollak Foundation for Economic Research (Box 51)
    - Public Affairs Committee (New York) (Box 51)
    - Public Affairs Institute (Box 51)
    - Research Council for Economic Security (Box 51)
    - Resettlement Administration (Box 51)
    - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 51)
    - Tennessee Valley Authority (Box 51)
    - United Public Health League (Box 51)
    - United State Chamber of Commerce (Box 51)
    - Welfare Council of New York (Box 51)
  - International Organizations
    - Fellowship for Freedom in Medicine (Box 51)
    - International Congress on Mental Health (Box 51)
    - International Hospital Federation (Box 51)
    - International Labour Office (Box 51)
    - World Federation of Trade Unions (Box 51)
    - World Health Organization (Box 51)
    - International Health Conference, 1946 (Box 51)
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) (Box 51)
  - Political Organizations
    - American Labor Party (Box 51)
    - CIO Political Action Committee (Box 51)
    - Democrats for '58 - Montgomery County Primary (Box 51)
    - Democratic National Committee, 1952, 1951, 1950, 1949, 1947 (Box 51)
    - Liberal Party of New York State (Box 51)
    - National Citizens Political Action Commmittee (Box 51)
    - Republican National Committee (Box 51)
    - Political Party Platforms (Box 51)
  - Committee for the Nation's Health
    - Committee for the Nation's Health (Box 53)
    - Executive Committee Members (Box 53)
    - Articles Promoted or Arranged for by CNH in Various Publications, 1948-1956 (Box 53-54)
    - Memos, Minutes, and Financial Statements (Box 54)
    - Honorary Vice Chairmen (Box 54)
    - Office Management and Taxes (Box 54)
  - Committee on Research in Medical Economics
    - CRME Minutes, Reports, 1939-1949 (Box 55)
    - CRME Projects (Box 55-56)
  - American Medical Association
    - Organization of the A.M.A. (Box 56-57)
    - Medical Societies - State and County (Box 57)
    - Public Relations (Box 57-58)
    - A.M.A. - C.N.H. - C.R.M.E. (Box 59)
    - A.M.A. - Record (Box 60)
    - A.M.A. Policy Re: Legislation and Related Matters (Box 60)
    - A.M.A. in Politics (Box 60)
    - Whitaker and Baxter (Box 60)
    - National Physicians Committee (Box 61)
  - Medical Associations other than the AMA
    - American Academy of General Practice (Box 61)
    - American Academy of Pediatrics (Box 61)
    - American Board of Internal Medicine (Box 61)
    - American College of Radiology (Box 61)
    - American College of Surgeons (Box 61)
    - American Medical Political Action Committee, 1961 (Box 61)
    - Association of American Physicians and Surgeons (Box 61)
    - Association of Interns and Medical Students (AIMS) (Box 61)
    - Committee of Physicians for the Improvement of Medical Care (Box 61)
    - Independent Committee of Colored Physicians (Box 61)
    - Medical Veterans Society (Box 61)
    - National Doctors Committee for the Improvement of Federal Medical Service (Box 61)
    - Oregon Physicians Fighting Political Medicine (Box 61)
    - Physicians Forum (Box 61)
    - Physicians Guild (Box 61)
- Medical Care in Foreign Countries, Series 5
  Divided into nine subseries, each containing multiple subject catalogued files.
  This series contains much public documentation and correspondence with leaders and private physicians concerned with social medicine and public health abroad. Most of these folders are devoted to the era in Great Britain that preceded and followed the Beveridge Plan, and are abundantly supplemented by comments (in print and letter form) made by practitioners, consultants, and specialists referring to the National Health Service Act and all aspects of its administration. There is a long correspondence with Sidney Lamb, one-time secretary of the International Hospital Association and secretary of the Merseyside Hospitals Council (Liverpool) who devoted so many years to the cause of improved hospital care in Great Britain and elsewhere, a correspondence containing warm and sensitive expressions of hopefulness for "the health help needed by the people of all countries."
  Much of the foreign material from Great Britain, the Continent, Asia, Africa, Canada, Australia, and New Zealand appears in the form of published and unpublished reports, most of it probably not duplicated in other collections on the social and economic aspects of medicine, health insurance, etc. One especially interesting part of the files at this point is correspondence and other material originating in the United States and commenting on the National Health Service in Great Britain -- a remarkable display of varieties of opinion both favorable and hostile.
  - Great Britain
    - England Before Beveridge (Box 61)
    - Ireland (Box 62)
    - Scotland (Box 62)
    - England from Beveridge on (Box 62-63)
    - NHS Controversy - British (Box 63)
    - Current NHS Material brought by MMD, 1960 (Box 63-64)
    - NHS Controversy - US (Box 64)
  - New Zealand
    - New Zealand (Box 64)
  - Australia
    - Australia (Box 64)
  - Asia and Africa
    - East-Indies (Box 64)
    - India (Box 64)
    - Israel (Box 64)
    - Japan (Box 64)
    - Liberia (Box 65)
    - South Africa (Box 65)
    - Syria (Box 65)
    - China (Box 65)
  - Canada
    - Reports (Box 65)
    - Canadian Sickness Survey, 1950-1951 (Box 65)
    - Pamphlets (Box 65)
    - Various Articles, 1948- (Box 65)
    - Various Articles, 1940 (Box 65)
    - Canadian Dental Association (Box 65)
    - Canadian Medical Association (Box 65)
    - Canadian Welfare Council (Box 65)
    - Toronto: Associated Medical Services of (Box 65)
    - Hospital Care Insurance in Canada (Box 65)
    - Health Sciences Center, University of British Columbia (Box 65)
- Personalities, Series 6
  Contains folders for 74 individuals.
  Arranged alphabetically by surname.
  The series on Personalities contains Dr. Davis' correspondence, notes, comments, clippings, personality evaluations, and memorabilia to, from, and about all of the leaders associated with him in his multifarious activities. Some individuals represented include Elin Anderson whose grass-roots pioneering efforts brought more adequate medical service to thousands of people in the United States; other names follow in a list of movers and shakers on the social scene there, such as: Dr. Georger Baehr, Harry Becker, Dr. George Berry, George Bugbee, Morris L. Cooke, Thomas E. Dewey, Oscar Ewing, Dr. I. S. Falk (an exceptionally long file dating from 1933 to 1954), Dr. Channing Frothingham, Sir William Jameson, Mr. and Mrs. Albert D. Lasker, Dean Leonard Mayo, Dr. James C. McCann, Dr. Frederick D. Mott, Anna M. Rosenberg, Adlai Stevenson, Senator Robert Taft, President Harry S. Truman, Albert W. Whitney, and hundreds of others. Most of the files contain correspondence of greater or lesser significance; many are reflections of Dr. Davis' numerous activities and include his terse comments--sometimes kindly, sometimes stringent and critical.
  - Personalities
    - Altmeyer, Arthur J. (Box 68)
    - Anderson, Elin (Box 68)
    - Asgis, Alfred J. (Box 68)
    - Baehr, George, M.D. (Box 68)
    - Ballard, F.L. (Box 68)
    - Barrows, Samuel J. (Box 68)
    - Baruch, Bernard (Box 68)
    - Basch, Shirley (Box 68)
    - Beck, Dorothy Fahs (Box 68)
    - Becker, Harry (Box 68)
    - Berens, Dr. Conrad (Box 68)
    - Berge, Wendell (Box 68)
    - Bernays, Edward L. (Box 68)
    - Berry, George P., M.D. (Dean, Harvard Medical School) (Box 68)
    - Biemiller, Andrew (Box 68)
    - Billikopf, Jacob (Box 68)
    - Bishop, R.H. Jr., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Blakesley, Howard F. (Box 68)
    - Boas, Ernst P., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Bond, Earl D., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Bone, Hugh A. (Box 68)
    - Bousfield, M.O., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Bowler, John P., Dr. (Box 68)
    - Bradbury, Samuel, M.D. (Box 68)
    - Bradley, Richard M. (Box 68)
    - Brown, Percy (Box 68)
    - Brown, Philip King, M.D. (Box 68)
    - Bruno, Frank J. (Box 68)
    - Buben, Zdenka (Box 68)
    - Buerki, Robin C. (Box 68)
    - Burgee, George (Box 68)
    - Burney, L.E., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Burns, Craig, M.D. (Box 68)
    - Burns, Professor Eveline M. (Box 68)
    - Butler, Allan M., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Cabot, Hugh, M.D. (Box 68)
    - Cabot, Philip (Box 68)
    - Cabot, Richard, M.D. (Box 68)
    - Cannon, Ida M. (Box 68)
    - Carlton, Winslow (Box 68)
    - Chaddock, Prof. Robert E. (Box 68)
    - Chisholm, G.B., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Christie, Aurthur C., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Clague, Ewan (Box 68)
    - Cobb, W. Montague, M.D. (Box 68)
    - Codman, Mrs. E.A. (Box 68)
    - Coggeshall, Lowell T., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Cohen, Wilbur J. (Box 68)
    - Commager, Henry Steele (Box 68)
    - Cooke, Morris L. (Box 68)
    - Crain, Kenneth (Box 68)
    - Cruikshank, Nelson (Box 68)
    - Dammasch, F.H., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Davis, Elmer (Box 68)
    - Davis, Michael M., Jr. (Box 68)
    - Davison, Wilburt C., M.D. (Box 68)
    - Deutsch, Albert (Box 68)
    - DeVoto, Bernard (Box 68)
    - Dewey, Thomas E. (Box 68)
    - Dodd, Paul A. (Box 68)
    - Duncan, Robert T. (Box 68)
    - Dunn, Halbert (Box 69)
    - Edelman, John (Box 69)
    - Edwards, Frank (Box 69)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 69)
    - Evans, Lester, M.D. (Box 69)
    - Ewing, Oscar (Box 69)
    - Falk Foundation (Box 69)
    - Falk, I.S. (Box 69)
    - Fleming, Grant, M.D. (Box 69)
    - Flexner, Abraham (Box 69)
    - Flynn, John T. (Box 69)
    - Folsom, Marion B. (Box 69)
    - Ford, Mrs. Ellen J. (Box 69)
    - Friedman, Maurice H., M.D. (Box 69)
    - Frothingham, Channing (Box 69)
    - Gannett, William Channing (Box 69)
    - Garrison, Lloyd K. (Box 69)
    - George, Father Gordon (Box 69)
    - Ginzberg, Professor Eli (Box 69)
    - Goldmann, Franz, M.D. (Box 69)
    - Gregg, Alan, M.D. (Box 69)
    - Hall, Helen (Box 69)
    - Hamilton, Alice (Box 69)
    - Hansen, Horace (Box 69)
    - Harding, T. Swann (Box 69)
    - Harris, Seymour (Box 69)
    - Hawley, Paul R., M.D. (Box 69)
    - Health Institute, UAW-CIO, Detriot, 1943-1944 (Box 69)
    - Hektoen, Ludwig (Box 69)
    - Hellstrom, Marika (Box 69)
    - Henry Street Study (Box 69)
    - Heyd, Charles Gordon, M.D. (Box 69)
    - Hill, Charles, M.D. (Box 69)
    - Hillman, Sidney (Box 69)
    - Hoadley, George (Box 69)
    - Hoehler, Fred K. (Box 69)
    - Horder, Lord (Box 69)
    - Howard, Dean Donald S. (Box 69)
    - Howard University - School of Social Work (Box 70)
    - Huntington, Professor Emily H. (Box 70)
    - Jackson, Fred W., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Jameson, Sir Wilson (Box 70)
    - Jarrett, Mary (Box 70)
    - Johnson, Charles S., Fiske University (Box 70)
    - Jones, Arthur (Box 70)
    - Jones, E.W. (Box 70)
    - Kaiser, Henry J. (Box 70)
    - Kaiser, Henry J. Company (Box 70)
    - Keefer, Chester, M.D. (Box 70)
    - Keppel, F.P. (Box 70)
    - Kerr, Lorin E., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Kingsbury, John A. (Box 70)
    - Kingsley, J. Donald (Box 70)
    - Klarman, Herbert E. (Box 70)
    - Kramer, Nathan (Russelton Medical Group) (Box 70)
    - Kraus, Professor Hertha (Box 70)
    - Lasker, Mr. and Mrs. Albert D. (Box 70)
    - Lawrence, John V., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Lee, Roger I., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Lee, Russel V., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Lenin (Box 70)
    - Lewis, Alfred Baker (Box 70)
    - Loos, Clifford, M.D. (Box 70)
    - MacLean, Basil D., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Mackintosh, J.M., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Magnuson, Paul B., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Maisel, Albert Q. (Box 70)
    - Maslow, Harold (Box 70)
    - Mattngly, Thomas E., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Mayo, Charles W., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Mayo, Professor Leonard W. (Box 70)
    - McCann, James C., M.D. (Box 70)
    - McLean, Franklin C., M.D. (Box 70)
    - McNary, William S. (Box 70)
    - Means, James Howard, M.D. (Box 70)
    - Medical Service Plans Conference, 1942 (Box 70)
    - Meek, Howard B. (Box 70)
    - Mercer, A.M., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Meriam, Lewis (Box 70)
    - Meyer, Max ("History in the Making") (Box 70)
    - Morgan, Gerald (Box 70)
    - Morse, Senator Wayne (Box 70)
    - Moseley, Charles H. (Box 70)
    - Mott, Fred D., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Mountain, Joseph W., M.D. (Box 70)
    - Munger, Charles H. (Box 70)
    - Murray, Senator James E. (Box 70)
    - Nelson, Russel A. (Box 70)
    - New England Journal of Medicine (Box 70)
    - New Republic (Box 70)
    - New York Times (Box 70)
    - Orr, Douglas, M.D. (Box 71)
    - Osler, William (Box 71)
    - Palmer, Robert C. and Mrs. Lewis E. (Box 71)
    - Parran, Thomas, M.D. (Box 71)
    - Parsons, Talcott (Box 71)
    - Patterson, Chat (Box 71)
    - Pearson, Drew (Box 71)
    - Pearson, John (Box 71)
    - Pearson, Leon M. (Box 71)
    - Peebles, Allon (Box 71)
    - Peixotto, Jessica B. (Box 71)
    - Pepper, Senator Claude (Box 71)
    - Perrott, George St. J., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Peters, John P., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Phillips, Herbert E. (Box 71)
    - Phillips, Wilbur C. (Box 71)
    - Pilcher, Jean, M.D. (Box 71)
    - Pink, Louis H. (Box 71)
    - Plumley, Margaret L. (Box 71)
    - Polakov, Walter N. (Box 71)
    - Potter, Ellen C., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Proger, Samuel, M.D. (Box 71)
    - Putnam, William F., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Rappleye, Dr. Willard C. (Box 71)
    - Reed, Lowell (Box 71)
    - Reidy, William G. (Box 71)
    - Roberts, Kingsley, M.D. (Box 71)
    - Robin, Frederick E. (Box 71)
    - Robins, R.B., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Robinson, Claude (Box 71)
    - Robinson, Dr. Miles H. (Box 71)
    - Roche, Josephine (Box 71)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano (Box 71)
    - Rosenberg, Anna (Box 71)
    - Rosenman, Samuel J. (Box 71)
    - Rosenwald, Julius (Box 71)
    - Rusk, Howard A., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Saltzstein, Harry C., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Sanger, Margaret (Box 71)
    - Sartain, Geraldine (Sartain Handbook) (Box 71)
    - Sawyer, William A., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Seham, Max (Box 71)
    - Shadid, Michael, M.D. (Box 71)
    - Searon, Marjorie (Box 71)
    - Sigerist, Henry E., M.D. (Box 71)
    - Smith, Henry Clay, M.D. (Box 71)
    - Stasson, Harold E. (Box 71)
    - Stein, Margaret (Box 71)
    - Stevenson, Adlai (Box 71)
    - Stillman, Calvin D. (Box 71)
    - Stokes, Thomas L. (Box 71)
    - Taft, Senator Robert A. (Box 71)
    - Tead, Ordway (Box 71)
    - Thompson, Mrs. Lewis S. (Box 71)
    - Truman, Harry S. (26 folders) (Box 72)
    - Van Steenwyck, E.A. (Box 72)
    - Wallace, Henry A. (Box 72)
    - Warren, Earl (Box 72)
    - Wagner, Seantor Robert F.S., Sr. (Box 72)
    - Whitney, Albert W. (Box 72)
    - Wilinsky, Charles F., M.D. (Box 72)
    - Williams, Greer (Box 72)
    - Williams, James M. (Box 72)
    - Williams, R.C., M.D. (Box 72)
    - Wilson, Charles E. (Box 72)
    - Winslow, C.E.A., M.D. (Box 72)
    - Yoell, Rodney, M.D. (Box 72)
    - Zimmer, Verne A. (Box 72)
Provenance
Donated to the New York Academy of Medicine Library by Michael Marks Davis in 1962.